<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Personal site of Patrick Canfield]]></title><description><![CDATA[Personal site of Patrick Canfield]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Sep 2018 02:21:30 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Surf Queen]]></title><description><![CDATA[This one is actually from a couple weeks ago. The model was wearing mermaid earrings and a necklace referencing St Christopher, the patron…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/7/28</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/7/28</guid><pubDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/2018-7-28-9357506b88f537a435b5268e6c84520d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Surf Queen&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is actually from a couple weeks ago. The model was wearing mermaid earrings and a necklace referencing St Christopher, the patron saint of surfers, she said. She said she was going for a regal expression, so I added the tiara.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazing how much making art with surf imagery awakened my own memories of when I used to surf in the warmer, gentler waves of Florida.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[New stuff]]></title><description><![CDATA[Okay, it’s been a while. I’ve still been making art, just haven’t been updating the blog. I’ve been saying “yes” a lot lately, maybe too…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/7/27</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/7/27</guid><pubDate>Fri, 27 Jul 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Okay, it’s been a while. I’ve still been making art, just haven’t been updating the blog. I’ve been saying “yes” a lot lately, maybe too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s my latest portrait from last night’s class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/2018-7-27-346c34c5d072eddc7bee8870cd6d749f.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Profile with dramatic lighting&quot;&gt;
I was sitting almost exactly opposite of the light source, so that was fun. Still getting better at being less representational and intentionally leaving artifacts which signify that this is a human’s attempt to represent something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you have a minute and a half to waste, you can watch &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/user87775051/review/282012329/c1e07dc4ad&quot;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt; of the creation process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made another yet-to-be-posted portrait last week, but I’ll wait until tomorrow to post that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tangentially related, but the space where the class is held is called Syzygy. The mastermind behind Syzygy was at the class last night talking about how his mission is to foster the local arts scene. He wants everyone to know that the scene in San Francisco is not dead! He plans to use the space to help emerging artists practice and gain exposure.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Let's get abstract]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Portrait of a model named KT 
God contemplating the fate of Donald Trump I’m getting better at being less representational in my art. It’s…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/7/15</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/7/15</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jul 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/2018-7-15-portrait-08e6f7b0fdbd25f13dd677241a60c3d2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Portrait of a model named KT&quot;&gt;
Portrait of a model named KT&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/2018-7-15-figure-91b50d7acf14b770b0ccb9e451e30794.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;God contemplating the fate of Donald Trump&quot;&gt;
God contemplating the fate of Donald Trump&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m getting better at being less representational in my art. It’s like swimming in the ocean and gradually getting comfortable with being farther and farther from shore. Eventually I’ll let go completely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is from the weekly portrait class. I’m happy about the more visible brush strokes that still manage to suggest form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is from a figure drawing class. It reminded me of the Calvin and Hobbes strips where Calvin imagines himself as the vengeful god of his imaginary universe, so I tried to emulate Waterson’s style in those strips.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Chance encounter]]></title><description><![CDATA[Sadly, when I first passed by in my pre-caffeinated haze, I mistook them as another group of vagrants up to mischief on the sidewalk outside…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/7/11</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/7/11</guid><pubDate>Wed, 11 Jul 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Sadly, when I first passed by in my pre-caffeinated haze, I mistook them as another group of vagrants up to mischief on the sidewalk outside of Bean Bag Cafe, where I was heading to putz around over coffee for a while. They were doing something with old wood and glass window panes, which were leaned against an old minivan full of unspecified urban detritus. I sat down in the back of the cafe, next to the back door which happened to open to the area where they were working. Then I noticed something odd: the glass of the windows appeared to have been painted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I walk outside to investigate. The windows indeed serve as substrates for vibrant paintings, featuring familiar vistas from around San Francisco. Turns out one of the two is blues musician turned painter &lt;a href=&quot;https://hoodline.com/2016/04/meet-chris-duke-blues-musician-window-art&quot;&gt;Chris Duke&lt;/a&gt;. He’s busy painting the wooden frames white and scraping the excess off the edges of the glass. The other introduces herself as Amy. Bean Bag was nice enough to let them work on their stretch of sidewalk. She explains that Chris paints on the reverse side of the glass, requiring him to think in reverse. On ordinary substrates like canvas you start by painting the background and work your way forward, but when painting on the back of glass you start with the foreground. They’re preparing some pieces that they hope will be selected for the new Transbay Terminal. There’s some kind of event where artists bring pieces before the people who get to decide this kind of thing. I hope they get some works in there. Window panes salvaged from old Victorian houses would be a great juxtaposition to the sleek modern transit terminal and a nice homage to a symbol of old San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video about Chris Duke by the San Francisco Chronicle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe height=&quot;432&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Uyba6zFCYDM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Flower Piano]]></title><description><![CDATA[In the botanical garden, pianos are distributed throughout as if sprouted from seeds, inviting any wandering maestros to give a performance…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/7/10</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/7/10</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/2018-7-10-31c58e07a28190dd8ae81781999d3e00.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;my sketch of one of these so-called flower pianos&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the botanical garden, pianos are distributed throughout as if sprouted from seeds, inviting any wandering maestros to give a performance. I meander until I find a pond under a canopy of trees. In the middle of the pond, a piano hides on a tiny boardwalk. I tramp along the pond’s edge,  happening upon a comfortable rock with a nice view. Some other artists are already camped out a few feet away. As I pull out my iPad, a familiar melody issues from the piano. It takes a minute for me to recognize that it’s Nirvana’s Smells Like Teen Spirit. It never occurred to me that grunge could sound so good on a classical instrument. The hidden pianos will be there at San Francisco botanical garden until July 16th and it’s free for city residents!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Slowly but surely getting decent at (digital) painting]]></title><description><![CDATA[Last night I went to portrait drawing class, that is, people sitting around in a room making representations of a model sitting in a…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/7/6</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/7/6</guid><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jul 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Last night I went to portrait drawing class, that is, people sitting around in a room making representations of a model sitting in a director’s chair somewhere in the middle, with some music playing for inspiration. It meets every week at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/Syzygy-Academy/&quot;&gt;a new community space&lt;/a&gt; focused on fostering the local arts scene by tailoring its services to the aspiring artist more than the established artist. This week I made perhaps my best portrait yet of the dozen or so times I’ve attended. I think what small amount of the painting class at CCSF I did attend helped in that I knew how to break the problem down in to smaller parts. I started by making a drawing of the model, then laid down flat regions of color, then applied tint and shading. I had a better idea of what qualities make a painting good, such a varying techniques of applying paint. One thing I noticed the other more experienced painters doing that would have made this painting better is capturing the slight variations in the hue of regions that at first blush seem like the same color, for example, the slight reddening of the face around the center of the cheeks and the tip of the nose. Also I’m still striving to get that “painterly” look where the fact that it’s a painting is obvious due to the chunky brush strokes, but when you step back the represented object emerges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/2018-7-06-c19afc4fa15d6211890ee971c13206de.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;my painting&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My painting, made on my iPad Pro with a program called Procreate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always tell myself that I’m making progress when I show up and practice, and that thought in itself is a great psychological refuge when it seems like nothing else is going in the right direction. It’s especially nice when I can see evidence that this thought is true, and last night, after the class, I decided to take the cable car over the hill instead of walking to celebrate.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Contrasting experiences]]></title><description><![CDATA[Yesterday a couple friends and I went on a bike ride that took us across the Golden Gate Bridge, to the top of  a mountain  where it was…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/7/5</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/7/5</guid><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jul 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday a couple friends and I went on a bike ride that took us across the Golden Gate Bridge, to the top of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mount_Tamalpais&quot;&gt;a mountain&lt;/a&gt; where it was unpleasantly cold and windy, then down to a beach where we passed out in the sun for a couple hours before hopping back on the bike to ride along the coast back to the city. The day before that I was visiting a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.noisebridge.net/wiki/Noisebridge&quot;&gt;a “doocratic” (i.e. anarchic) hacker space&lt;/a&gt; where I learned about how such a place functions as well as video game development. It’s such contrasting experiences like these, in such a short time frame, that make me feel that the 62% higher rent and everything else I put up with to live here is somewhat justified. This post is super short and more incomplete than usual because the juices just don’t seem to be flowing today. Perhaps I’ll expand on it another day. For now, here’s some pictures from the ride:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/2018-7-4-strava-da43691c521edf0a96ec0629785a5c13.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Stravas&quot;&gt;
Our route according to Strava&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/2018-7-4-faces-8813948371b575803c4690ed81576977.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The end is near?&quot;&gt;
Are we there yet??&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Zen and the art of giving a f***]]></title><description><![CDATA[Last night I attended a “sit” at a  Zen meditation center , as has been my custom lately. The “sit” is a 30 minute meditation. Sometimes it…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/7/3</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/7/3</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jul 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Last night I attended a “sit” at a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.againstthestream.org/&quot;&gt;Zen meditation center&lt;/a&gt;, as has been my custom lately. The “sit” is a 30 minute meditation. Sometimes it’s guided, but this time it’s completely silent. Afterwards &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.againstthestream.org/teacher/matthew-brensilver/&quot;&gt;the facilitator&lt;/a&gt; fields questions from those gathered. The greeter by the door, bald with a black fedora, stands up and asks a great question. The gist of it: how should a good Buddhist (substitute Buddhist for human if you want, it makes no difference to me) be politically informed without letting the fear and outrage-driven news industry compromise your well-being? The facilitator answers in two parts. One, through the practice of meditation we build up a supply of well-being that we have an obligation to use, not keep to ourselves. Two, in difficult times such as these, people with a good heart &lt;em&gt;ought&lt;/em&gt; to be suffering, for the sake of all sentient life. As the world outside continues to spin out of control, with apathy and distrust seemingly on the rise, I feel inspired to recommit to being less self-centered, giving more of myself, and being at peace with my limited sphere of influence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Update: after reflecting on it a bit more, my mind snapped in to place something else the facilitator said that at the time seemed unrealated to the above: “What we don’t listen to, we become.” He was talking about how, as an individual, the thoughts that we allow to run wild in our subconscious end up influencing our destiny, for better or worse. Meditation is basically listening, like a good friend, to the mental activity that normally goes unnoticed. It’s only once we’re aware of a tendancy in ourselves that we can choose to change it. Perhaps this concept can be applied to a society as well as to an individual. Perhaps the news media forms part of our collective (sub?)conscious. It’s unpleasant to tune in to, but we need to in order to sort the real problems from the scare du jour, and to intellegently engage in political conversations.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[ZzzzEO]]></title><description><![CDATA[I don’t have any ideas today, so I’m just going to write about my dream last night. In my dream I was the CEO of a company with hundreds of…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/7/2</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/7/2</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I don’t have any ideas today, so I’m just going to write about my dream last night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my dream I was the CEO of a company with hundreds of employees and I was thinking wow, I finally have a job that I really enjoy and the pay isn’t bad either. It’s hard to remember why I liked it, not sure if it was just the perks, or the freedom to execute my ideas with the resources of a company at my disposal. I only went to the meetings I was interested in, I had assistants to do the stuff I don’t enjoy doing. Perhaps what I liked was that every day I had a mostly full schedule (managed by assistants) of mostly interesting activities. My job frequently required getting out of the office and meeting contacts at a variety of locations. Sometimes lunch at a fine dining establishment, sometimes a behind-the-scenes industrial setting of some sort. It required being creative, a lot of reading and writing, connecting people, thinking big. It was weird because being a CEO was never something I aspired to, but if it’s really like that then maybe I’ll keep it in mind just in case I ever come across a “CEO wanted” sign. Those exist, right?&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Why]]></title><description><![CDATA[What hubris. Publishing a blog at a website named after yourself? Adding to the ever-growing ocean of information whatever commonplace…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/7/1</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/7/1</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;What hubris. Publishing a blog at a website named after yourself? Adding to the ever-growing ocean of information whatever commonplace thought crosses your mind? For whom? Who cares? Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’re looking at it all wrong. It’s not for anyone but myself, and if anyone else reads it, great. The idea is to be “process oriented” rather than results oriented, to practice getting thoughts out of my head and into words. If the results are not remarkable, that’s fine, but the possibility that they might be, eventually, provides a little extra motivation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.akimbo.me/blog/season-2-episode-1-permission-and-seo-and-blogs&quot;&gt;this podcast episode from Seth Godin&lt;/a&gt; I’m going to try to write something, no matter how inspired or smart I feel, every day. Because I like ideas. I like other people’s ideas, but only consuming other people’s ideas gets old after a while. I believe in the idea, which is echoed by Seth and many others, that the best way to have ideas is to write, and write a lot. Though originality is a fuzzy notion, I feel confident in saying this particular post has zero original ideas, but if I keep restating unoriginal ideas long enough, eventually whether by accident or insight I’ll say something sort of novel.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Back at it]]></title><description><![CDATA[Hey, it’s been a while. Since my last entry I started and finished a contract job. It wasn’t the kind of work that I really want to do, but…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/6/27</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/6/27</guid><pubDate>Wed, 27 Jun 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Hey, it’s been a while. Since my last entry I started and finished a contract job. It wasn’t the kind of work that I really want to do, but I learned a lot (mainly about the nature of contract work) and was compensated well enough that I have time to figure out my next steps. What did I learn? For one, it’s hard to help people who don’t know what they want. The end-client was a startup who’s CEO just couldn’t commit to a design, and kept asking for changes mid-implementation. I got better at anticipating possible design changes and writing code that minimizes the difficulty of making such changes. I also learned the value of managers, of which there were none on this project. If there was a manager, she would have established norms that maximize productivity. For example, when you have a non-urgent work request, you put it in some kind of shared tracking system. Preferably, there is only one such system that everyone uses. What you &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; do is go drop by the desk of the person who you think is right for the job and interrupt whatever task he’s currently working on. Such an asynchronous process is more efficient because task switching is hard. It’s hard on the mind of a programmer who needs to hold of lot of information in his working memory, information that’s different from one task to another. My client had multiple systems for tracking work, and they still did the dreaded drop-bys. A programmer’s nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not that I was perfect. If I were to do it all over again I would have taken more care with my initial time estimate. They presented me with complete “pixel perfect” designs for the entire website. They told me they needed it in a month. I looked it over for about 10 minutes and told them I could do it. Two months later, and with one additional contractor on the job, it was finally mostly done. Though the water is muddied a bit by the design changes (see above paragraph) I was wildly optimistic in my initial estimate. If I find myself in such a situation again I would spend a whole day analyzing the design, sort of implementing it in my head, to arrive at a more accurate estimate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess because the project was so behind schedule, the client was threatening to not pay me for half of the work I did for them. Thankfully, just today, before writing this, I received half of that withheld half, and it looks like I will get the other quarter of the total soon enough. It’s a weight lifted off my shoulders. Still, I didn’t go to the beginning painting class I enrolled in for the summer at the city college today because I was sure the client wouldn’t pay me and consequently I would have to scramble to find another job. I was already falling behind in the painting class, and I think missing today just put the nail in the coffin. I think I prefer digital painting anyway. I realized that painting with real paint required a lot of technical knowledge about pigments, substrates, brushes etc but I just want to make images. There’s a parallel to my day job. Creating software also requires a lot of technical knowledge. There are substrates to know about like hardware platforms, software platforms. There are brushes like compilers, IDEs. There are pigments like programming languages, techniques, paradigms… So far no one has managed to create software that allows a designer to create software without technical knowledge, but when it comes to painting I have my iPad Pro + Pencil which allows me create while being blissfully unaware of the underlying complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m thinking my next step is a lateral move in to video game development. It’s what got me interested in programming in the first place. My young imagination was sparked playing games like Super Mario, Pokemon, and a slew of titles for MS-DOS and Windows (Anyone remember Grim Fandango?) As a super geeky middle schooler I taught myself BASIC and ActionScript and struggled to wrap my mind around C++. There are a plethora of game development shops here in San Francisco, from the massive public companies like Disney/LucasArts to tiny indie game firms. Just today I was talking to an acquaintance who, as it turns about, spent eight years in the game industry. He offered to connect me with people who might be hiring, so I’m about to drop him a line. Anyway, that’s my game plan, and a bad plan is better than no plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S. I wasn’t sure how to work this in to the above, but I’ve been posting my art to my Instagram and thinking of it as my online portfolio. You can check it out &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/patreeceeo/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Fostering creativity in the Excelsior district of San Francisco]]></title><description><![CDATA[A resident I met that day described it as hell’s armpit. Though perhaps she meant it in a good way. I was in one of the last working class…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/3/29/fostering-creativity-excelsior</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/3/29/fostering-creativity-excelsior</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Mar 2018 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;A resident I met that day described it as hell’s armpit. Though perhaps she meant it in a good way. I was in one of the last working class neighborhoods left in San Francisco, at an event called Sunday Streets, which monthly hops from neighborhood to neighborhood transforming one of its main streets in to a street fair, inviting local organizations to create a physical presence to engage with the community. I was volunteering with an organization called ArtSpan. We wanted to get the message out that we’re renovating the neighborhood’s old defunct hospital building to be our new home which will offer community programs and studio space for artists and other efforts to keep art alive in San Francisco, thanks to a low interest lease from the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To watercolor paint in spray bottles, various wooden shapes for doing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resist&quot;&gt;resist&lt;/a&gt;, pens, brushes, little blank white canvases with convenient built-in keyhole fittings for hanging up we dedicated one of our tables so we could invite passers by, especially children, to create a masterpiece they can take home. And create they did. I was blown away by the worthy art they created. Young and old, black, white, Latino, Asian, etc they came, they saw, they painted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/artspan-table-cd978ca52d4e6e8ee496d0c2cded53f8.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;ArtSpan table&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stood in front of the tent, trying various tactics to get people’s attention and convince them to give it a try. I drew an advertisement on the asphalt with some of the colored chalk floating around. I held up finished pieces and waved them at the crowds. I thought I could sense something, fear or uncertainty, with some people. They seemed to want to participate but something held them back. It was easier to melt this inhibition with the kids, showing them how much fun people were having. With the adults, the defenses seemed much thicker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chalk-drawing-9d2edaa45c0dcc8c9015d9370a98449e.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;#x22;Art this way&amp;#x22; chalk drawing&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team consisted entirely of volunteers like myself. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amyahlstrom.com/&quot;&gt;Amy, a real professional artist&lt;/a&gt; was the mastermind and ringleader of our operation. She recounted how she had this idea, knew it would cost a lot, but ArtSpan anted up to make it possible. Her good vibes and enthusiasm, she was a school teacher for many years, really helped keep people engaged and having fun once I snagged their attention. There was also live painting by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nicolevismara.com/&quot;&gt;Nicole Vismara&lt;/a&gt; to help get people’s attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/artspan-table-sideview-62c2764d83ad67e574a318fc2eb841a2.png&quot; alt=&quot;ArtSpan table, again&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/live-painting-bb4e838b1558260508092078bd6cdb5e.png&quot; alt=&quot;Live painting&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the show was drawing to a close, the MC on the live music stage thanked the audience for keeping the Excelsior real. This is what “real” means, I thought as I walked back to where I parked my bike. In the slanted golden afternoon sunbeams I saw life being lived on the sidewalks. Folks just chatting, getting their hair cut, kids playing, a few broken windows, and a conspicuous absence of new housing developments, shiny new coffee shops, Disneyland for well-healed millennials, etcetera, etcetera. I felt a raw striving energy, a bittersweet happiness. Something about it stole a piece of my heart. The name Excelsior can mean “excellent”, as well as “ever upward”. It’s already lived up to the first sense, in my opinion. I hope the name is prophetic in the second sense only if it doesn’t entail the creative destruction that has effected so many other parts of this city. What is too often destroyed is what gives the city that ineffable quality referred to as “soul”. I know this is an old story, that San Francisco isn’t what it used to be. I’ve heard it over and over again since moving here and often worried that I was part of the problem. The experience of volunteering and the prospective creation of the Onondaga Art Center in the old hospital building has given me more hope than anything else that the best parts of the old San Francisco are still alive, like hot coals hiding under the ashes of a mostly extinguished fire. A fire which can be rekindled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These past few weeks I’ve watched my monetary wealth steadily decline due to my determination to do only what I really care about, regardless of the compensation, for as long as I can manage to do so. As I rode home in the late afternoon sunlight through the hills of the outskirts of town I felt wealthy with renewed faith, passion and purpose.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[A dharma bum afternoon]]></title><description><![CDATA[Things had come to a head. My head, to be exact. They were prancing about and demanding my attention. I had decided to go home early because…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/3/24</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/3/24</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2018 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Things had come to a head. My head, to be exact. They were prancing about and demanding my attention. I had decided to go home early because I could no longer feel the importance of anything. There I curled up in bed with a book and put on the radio. I think I should have taken a nap earlier in the day to maximize my productivity, but the sun coming through my westward window is gently massaging my back with its rays and I let sleep carry me away and back again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a while I’m hungry so I fire up the oven and put in that bread dough from yesterday even though it &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; rise for two days, ideally. I go back to my book and now I’m lying in full toasty sunshine. Then the sunny patch moves on to the floor, to my meditation spot. I finish the chapter and follow it, asking Alexa to stop the music. I can smell the bread in the oven as I try to meditate. And hear the crackling of the ice cubes I put in a pan under the bread because supposedly that helps make the crust extra crispy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just then I feel so remarkably on good terms with life and everything in it I just had to get up and try to put words to this feeling. I realize I was being too rough on myself with piles of shoulds and oughts. I had forgotten that I have to be gentle in order to hear that wisdom which speaks in a whisper, which keeps me on course like a rudder.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Getting cultured, on a dime]]></title><description><![CDATA[So I went on a little adventure last month. I’m posting this a month after the fact because I wanted to finish this thing I made to…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/2/13/art-in-tenderloin</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/2/13/art-in-tenderloin</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2018 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;div replace-with=&quot;PhotoMap2&quot; props=&quot;ArtInTenderloin&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I went on a little adventure last month. I’m posting this a month after the fact because I wanted to finish this thing I made to accompany this blog post. Been putting in a couple hours a day a few days a week. What is it? A box that shows photos (which I took with my phone) and places them on a map using the data embedded in the digital file format (EXIF). Now that I’ve got this I want to start using it in more posts that weave together photos, reflections and specific locations in San Francisco and perhaps beyond. And perhaps make other cool map things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, about my field trip. There’s this organization called ArtSpan which does a lot to nourish and promote the (visual) arts community here in San Francisco. One of those things is a program called Art in Neighborhoods, which showcases pieces by local artists in hotel lobbies, cafes and such. I happened to notice it while browsing ArtSpan’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artspan.org/home&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; and decided to go see how many of the pieces I could see myself. I felt a little self-conscious walking in to lobbies of hotels that I wasn’t checked in to, but I strode in like I belonged there. I regarded it as an exercise in acting cool and seemly. The hotel staff probably didn’t care anyway. And hypothetically I could have been there to purchase some art, I thought as I sipped iced lemon water and stared at the stormy composition by Anna-Lena Sauer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My adventure took me around a central neighborhood known as the Tenderloin, (in)famous for great food and cultural attractions juxtaposed to extremely visible homelessness and drug abuse. There was one location, an actual art gallery, CounterPulse, where it seemed to be closed contrary to information online and I didn’t bother investigating much because the scene outside was a bit too raw and I was too uncomfortable. I guess I was just afraid of being singled out by one of those people who suffer from delusions and verbal outbursts. Otherwise I had a pleasant time walking from spot to spot, enjoying the ubiquitous murals so I was practically swimming in art.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[A tale of art, psychology, San Francisco and Burrito Project]]></title><description><![CDATA[I was at  Burrito Project  the other day, a non-profit that gathers volunteers at Martin de Porres house of hospitality on the last Monday…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/02/03/burrito-project</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/02/03/burrito-project</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Feb 2018 07:11:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I was at &lt;a href=&quot;https://burritoprojectsf.org/&quot;&gt;Burrito Project&lt;/a&gt; the other day, a non-profit that gathers volunteers at Martin de Porres house of hospitality on the last Monday of each month to assemble and deliver burritos to the homeless or merely house-less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it’s my first time delivering burritos, the coordinators pair me with a veteran. Mine has longish brown hair that weaves its way down to just above the scarf wrapped jauntily around his nape, a knowing smile and a few more years than myself. Ken’s his name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s people delivering on foot, and bicyclists like Ken and myself. We’re the last to get to the burrito supply, and what’s left seems so puny in comparison with our massive carrying capacity that Ken decides to go sweet talk someone at the end of the assembly line. He returns victorious, with a full box of hot foil-wrapped love capsules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We get rolling as the sun is setting. Ken leading the way, we cross the rush hour traffic on Potrero Avenue more daringly than I would have on my own. We’re heading to the “hairball”, the intersection of Cesar Chavez and Bayshore Freeway, where homeless encampments clog the pedestrian pathways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“How long have you lived here?” Ken inquires, once we’re safely in the southbound bike lane. San Francisco is constantly reinventing itself, and you can infer, or assume, a lot about a person by what stage of the evolution welcomed them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Four years” I said. Turns out he’s resided here eight times longer than that, as long as I’ve been alive. And that he has to be more careful on his bike these days because the city has become so congested with street traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And what brought you here?” I tell him about visiting San Francisco on a trip while in college and felt an affinity to the place. Years later, after leaving a job, it seemed like as good a time as any to make the move. He’s glad to hear that people continue to move here out of a love of place. I don’t say that in that first several months I had a lot of mixed feelings, that the grime and stress and overwhelm drove me away. But the city had gotten into my bones, the way wild yeast gets in to sourdough, and I came running back. This place inspires me to make great art, write poems, and attempt other things I can’t do. I didn’t share any of this, but the important thing, a shared love, had been recognized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to Ken’s story, the cover did not mislead. He left New Jersey with Hollywood aspirations, took a detour through San Francisco and didn’t make it to Los Angeles until twenty years later. He now makes &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kenpaulrosenthal.com&quot;&gt;documentary films about mental health from a perspective known as radical psychology&lt;/a&gt;. Rather than pathologize emotional distress, the radical mental health movement considers madness largely as a reflection of a social condition, he explained. He also works as an Arts and Exhibition Preparator in a workshop for adults with developmental disabilities called, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.creativityexplored.org&quot;&gt;Creativity Explored&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We arrive at the hairball to find that the people living there had been “resolved” by SFPD, something a majority of legal residents voted in favor of but probably wouldn’t carry out themselves. As it turns out, there’s still a few of them huddled together in a cove created by the transportation infrastructure. You might think they looked threatening if you were just passing through in the shadowy night, but up close, with faces lit up by some foil-wrapped nourishment, I can’t help but feel some kinship. We rode on and pretty soon I spotted a tent by the athletic fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately I’ve been taking pains to be more aware of my surroundings, to see what’s actually there rather than what I’ve been conditioned to see by past experiences, to relish and be grateful for all that I have. Altruistic actions like Burrito Project are a good opportunity for that. Improving the powers of perception improves creativity as well as the ability to perform magic, the real kind. It’s part of a thesis I’ve been meditating on lately, the coalescence of a diverse bibliography: The Artist’s Way, Bacteria to Bach and Back, Siddhartha etc. I believe I’m not alone in my need for this kind of magic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hot burritos! Anyone in there hungry?” I say in the most non-threatening voice I could muster. A man’s head emerges, there’s a woman behind him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What is this? Oh my gawd yes!” I hand them both burritos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And what do you do?” Ken asks once we’re rolling again. I feel apprehensive. Seems there’s a severe allergy to technology professions that afflicts a lot of non-tech people in San Francisco, and not without reason. I guess it was thanks to our common appreciation for San Francisco that he didn’t write me off when I told him that I’m part of an internet startup. I could tell from his questions that he’s definitely outside the tech bubble, and probably doesn’t even watch Silicon Valley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But” I say, “I’m going to leave soon. I just can’t bring myself to focus on it anymore. I still like coding,” I explain, “but my ideal arrangement wouldn’t have me doing it full-time. I —“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I sense there’s a dream percolating there.” I’m glad for the interruption. I needed a second to gather my thoughts. Actually, I’m still meditating on that one. He’s right, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ve always had an artistic side.” I said, starting with what I’m most certain about. Ken was audibly pleased with that answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have a theory that the weather and landscape here fosters creativity. The weather is so strange and unpredictable, creating a sense of instability, which the hills and mountains contribute to…” We dismount as we approach another tent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It keeps things from getting routine.” I offer. I read somewhere that one of the necessary conditions for creativity is just enough random noise in the environment that helps the creative generate ideas, but not so much that they can’t actually get any work done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We come across several people living by the factory at 16th and Van Ness. One of them wants two burritos, then another, then another. He says they’re for so-and-so. Then he wants two more for some other buddies. We give them to him, asking him to just not let them go to waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next group we come across seems to have re-created a living room on the sidewalk by a boarded-up building. They’re wishy washy about the offer of burritos. One of them asks if they’re vegetarian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yep!” I said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Well I’m a meat eater. No thanks.” The others seem to follow his lead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We get back to Martin de Porres as the operation is shutting down. Ken goes to give some feedback to the coordinators about how to better handle the migrations of the homeless population. I get talking to someone else who says we gave out 530 burritos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s curious how sometimes you’re looking for something, and then when you’re not, it appears. During the ride Ken was telling me about how there’s still a thriving arts community here, despite the rampant gentrification. As we’re saying goodbye I ask Ken about his latest film &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.whisperrapture.com&quot;&gt;Whisper Rapture&lt;/a&gt;, a music and mental health doc-opera about cellist-vocalist, &lt;a href=&quot;http://bonfiremadigan.com/&quot;&gt;Bonfire Madigan Shive&lt;/a&gt; and he informs me of a lot of other interesting things to check out, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.againstthestream.org/centers/san-francisco/&quot;&gt;a meditation society founded by x-punk rockers&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artspan.org/events-programs/visit-sf-open-studios&quot;&gt;how to be privy to local artists’ open studios&lt;/a&gt;. I haven’t quite figured out what I want to be when I grow up, but I at least have some things I’m excited to explore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my ride to Burrito Project I noticed a van on the side of the road by a discount grocery store. It was advertising tamales, $2 each. Now that all the burritos are gone, I need to feed myself, so I track down that van. It seems like a husband and wife team. Strong Latin American accents, but I can understand just fine. I get the impression they don’t see many customers who look like me. I order one pork and one beef. They were delicious.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Sleep, mindfulness, and art]]></title><description><![CDATA[I finally feel like I’m winning the war against my insomnia. I’d been fighting this war for over two years and every night felt like a new…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/01/15/sleep-mindfulness-art</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2018/01/15/sleep-mindfulness-art</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 17:11:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I finally feel like I’m winning the war against my insomnia. I’d been fighting this war for over two years and every night felt like a new battle. Daily exercise helped a lot, but it seemed like I needed eight hours of exercise to buy eight solid hours of sleep. For a while I thought coffee was the enemy, but I love coffee and cutting it out didn’t consistently help. I made sure my room was dark and quiet but I’d still wake up in the middle of the night in fight-or-flight response. In retrospect, it seems obvious that meditation would be a promising solution-space. I realized that the problem was all in my mind. It was a habit of thought, which doesn’t make it any less of a real problem. I had such high expectations for myself every day that being delayed or inconvenienced for just a few seconds from the pursuit of my objectives felt like an impending personal doom. I strained my mind to figure out how to squeeze every ounce of productivity out of each day. This idea of hyper-productivity sort of took on a life of its own as an overbearing task-master, who would flip on the internal fluorescent lights and sound the alarm when I needed to be sleeping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being randomly invited on a meditation retreat in the Santa Cruz mountains was what clued me in. As I hinted at earlier, ideas are sort of alive. They’re also contagious. I had tried meditation before, but it never really stuck. It just felt like I was wasting time. In Santa Cruz, though, I was surrounded by people who “got” it and was immersed in their ideas about meditation and saw first hand that it’s not just a thing you do for a bit in the morning in the privacy of your bedroom, but a way of life. And I saw that it could be a lot of fun. And then I “got” it. I no longer saw meditation as something I &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; do, but something I &lt;em&gt;get&lt;/em&gt; to do. I don’t really understand how, but I feel like it’s more effective now. Now, after meditating, I feel like everything is quieter, slower, simpler, and more enjoyable. Since then I’ve done more research on my own and found that a blend of mindfulness meditation and compassion meditation for about 15 minutes to be hugely effective for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life rarely lets you change one variable at a time, though. Soon after the meditation retreat the startup I’m a part of started seeing some payoffs for our months of hard work, and I had enjoyed increased peace of mind concerning paying my bills. Without this peace of mind I may not have applied what I learned from the retreat as much as I have. Now that I have, though, I feel like I have the tools to prevent insomnia from become a big issue again. It didn’t start with the startup, and there will always be struggle and stress in life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently splurged on an iPad Pro because of the ease with which it lets me make art. I’ve found that it’s also arguably a kind of meditation. After using it I find that I’m more perceptive. I spend a lot of time writing computer code these days, which leaves me thinking and feeling more computer-like: differences below a certain threshold do not make a difference to me. But in the practice of making art, though, every detail in the subject is potentially important, and you have to train your mind to actually see those details. After drawing for a while I’m seeing the world as an artist, noticing things in my every day environment that I hadn’t noted before and seeing beauty everywhere. It doesn’t seem to matter that I’m making art with a computer. I guess the resolution is high enough and the inputs sensitive enough that to my brain it’s just like analog mediums. Also, it’s known that imagination and perception use the same circuitry in the brain, and learning to see as an artist again has helped me steal back control of that circuitry from an over-active imagination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is dedicated to my Uncle’s mother, who I’ve had the pleasure of meeting at two weddings in the past couple of years, and her family. Know that y’all have been in my thoughts and prayers lately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/rosebird-81111219a9e1be957498827c0b4fb634.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;pastel and ink on iPad&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[On the being and nothingness of Patrick / end of 2017 reflections]]></title><description><![CDATA[There’s a lot that I want to become, and its overwhelming when I try to conceive of what it would take to fulfill my most ambitious visions…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2017/12/28/new-years-2017</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2017/12/28/new-years-2017</guid><pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2017 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot that I want to become, and its overwhelming when I try to conceive of what it would take to fulfill my most ambitious visions of myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One good trick I’ve found that works for me personally is writing it all down. Once the words have been captured by paper and ink they seem more manageable, more well-behaved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This almost automatically leads to doing a little bit every day. Or most days. Be micro-ambitious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which reminds me of my third helpful tactic: embracing imperfection. If I’m making good choices &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; of the time, even just 51%, I’m doing just fine. This helps me avoid black and white thinking about myself: bad choices leading to thinking of myself as “bad”, which makes me more prone to more bad choices. Or, good choices leading to me thinking I deserve to make some bad choices. A relevant reflection: humans are the only animals that can suffer for things not happening now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are depressed you are living in the past. If you are anxious you are living in the future. If you are at peace you are living in the present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;― Lao Tzu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, we can also be happy about things not happening right now. I’m not sure how to synthesize that with the above, but I feel it’s an important point to note.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fourth practice is getting very, very clear about just what “good” is. Aristotle believed that truly knowing what is good necessarily leads to good action. While he might have overstated his case, I’ve found that the more clear I am about what I need to do, the easier it is to do it. One thing I’m that clear on is the importance of being well-rounded, not being pigeon-holed. I’m not sure why I want that so much, I just know I get really bored when there isn’t much change in my day-to-day work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My primary occupation these days is software engineer and co-founder of a startup, but I’m also interested in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;writing [active]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;drawing [active]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;mindfulness [active]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;physical fitness [active]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;learning to be more musical [inactive]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;overcoming stage fright / shyness [inactive]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;political activism [inactive]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the ones marked [active] I’ve been doing a little bit, most days, that is 51%. The political activism one really bothers me. I see so much happening that I feel is wrong, but because there’s so much happening relative to how much time I have to give, I get discouraged. The same principle of doing a little every day should apply, but for some reason it seems harder in this case. Perhaps because it’s a rabbit hole, and one I’ve been down before. But if something you love is being threatened, is there any justification for not doing &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;? Anyway, I hope by the end of 2018 I can consider myself active in those last three areas, especially the last.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Bikesgiving!]]></title><description><![CDATA[Above  an interactive map slash photo gallery of our adventure. Click on any photo to zoom in. You can also use your keyboard to switch…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2017/11/26/bikesgiving-2017</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2017/11/26/bikesgiving-2017</guid><pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2017 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;div replace-with=&quot;PhotoMap&quot; props=&quot;Bikesgiving&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Above&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; an interactive map slash photo gallery of our adventure. Click on any photo to zoom in. You can also use your keyboard to switch between photos:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;right arrow / enter / space =&gt; next photo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;left arrow =&gt; previous photo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;escape =&gt; view map&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;tl;dr&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Biked 171 miles over three days starting from Berkeley and finishing in San Francisco. Loved getting to see so much Northern California beauty on a bike, with no concerns and nothing to do but mash pedals and goof around, plus there’s a nice high you get from biking 50+ miles. It also makes me sleep like a baby. No, a rock. …a little baby rock. Can’t wait for the next multi-day bike adventure, TBD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;M&lt;/span&gt;y cousin, Tom, and I spent our Thanksgiving weekend on a little three day adventure by bicycle, and it was better than sweet potato casserole &lt;small&gt;[or insert your favorite Thanksgiving dish here]&lt;/small&gt;, and I love to eat. This cousin went by himself on a two day bike trip to Santa Cruz a few weeks earlier and crashed on my couch the night before. I was on the verge of dropping everything just to go with him, but I made an agreement with him and myself that we would go at the next opportunity, which turned out to be Thanksgiving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That Tuesday we meet a Finnegan’s Wake to hash out the details. The plan still feels hazy when I leave, but we at least had decided to start Thursday morning from Tom’s place in Berkeley and ride north, winding through wine country, then at some point veer west and meet up with the Pacific Coast Highway which would bring us to San Francisco on Saturday. I would crash on his couch the night before this time. As for sleeping the other nights, we decided to defer booking hotels and bring our camping stuff, so in the worst case we can find a secluded patch of forest to call home for a night. Having that option in our back pockets gives us flexibility with limited downside, but at the cost of carrying that extra stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I load up on shelf-stable foodstuffs from Trader Joe’s and buy some &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/B00JUGTX62/ref=TE_tex_dp_1&quot;&gt;pannier bags&lt;/a&gt; online to carry them and my camping stuff. A little anxious about the possibility of finding myself in the middle of nowhere with no snacks, though in retrospect its obvious the chances of that happening are slim to none. But, like I said, I really like to eat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We leave Thursday morning and rode north, just like we planned. The first several miles through Berkeley, El Cerrito, etc I’m ecstatic with anticipation for the adventures ahead. But the weight of doubt and of my pack hits me along with the first hill. All the stuff I’m carrying makes hills significantly more difficult to ascend. I fear winding up on the side of some massive hill, unable to pedal another foot, whereupon I suddenly, and with a loud thud, fall on my side. That never happens, as it turns out. I eat some of my snacks, my pack becomes lighter and I have more energy. A win-win-win solution!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside for a brief grind along highway 29 through American Canyon, the first morning is pleasant and peaceful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“B****TCH!” Someone has decided to share his feelings with me and has leaned out of a window to shout them. I’m in such a good mood that I just smile back. I register some dismay on his face just before he withdraws, as if that wasn’t the reaction he was looking for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While eating lunch in Napa, we decide to veer west a bit early and head towards Santa Rosa, where, through the wonders of the internet, we discover a hotel with vacancy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We rode through Sonoma, ravaged by the recent fires. Saw remains of houses with little more than a chimney to mark the ground somone once called home. A spray-painted sign hung on the fence around one such ruin reads “Still thankful.” We conclude the night with massive burritos and beers at a restuarant across the street from the hotel. I’m exhausted, but in a euphoric way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next morning we set out while the chilly fog yet hung about, lending a certain shadowy mystique to the agricultural landscape. Its just farmland and forests, hills and valleys, all the way to the costal highway. Cows and sheep are our only spectators today. There were a few hills that almost broke us, psychologically. It just made the view at the top all the more wonderous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We arrive at to Point Reyes Station, and though there’s still a few hours of daylight left, decide to hunker down there for the night. Having neglected to do so earlier, we pull out our smartphones to figure out where exactly that would be. It was looking bleak there for a bit, if you can call having to camp in the woods bleak. But we found a vacancy at a wonderful little &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.abaloneinn.com/&quot;&gt;bed and breakfast with a hottub&lt;/a&gt;, and surprisingly affordable. Sold! I could have slept on the park bench I was so zonked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next morning we ride down to Stinson Beach, where we eat lunch. Tom’s knees are bothering him, so we decide to “ride” to the top of Mount Tamalpais via bus. The bus arrives with one bike already on the rack. There’s only space for two. Maybe that bike’s owner is getting off, we hope. It becomes obvious that only one of us is getting on the bus, so I tell Tom to go ahead and I’ll meet him up there. Little did I know that the ride to the summit is at least an hour and a half long! I knew it would be a slog, but not such a long one. I tried my darnedest to catch up with him, but by the time I was half way up the mountain he had already waited for a while and rode on to Sausilito, several miles from the Golden Gate Bridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up to this point the trip had been perfect, I can’t imagine it going any better. If I could do it again I would skip the summit and instead ride to Sausilito to meet up with Tom so we could ride across the bridge and finish the ride together. I never ended up catching up with him, he was exhausted and wanted to go home. I did make it to the top of Mount Tamalpais, so I was rewared with an expansive view of the bay area, but I think the sense of accomplishment from us riding across the bridge together would have been greater. I tend to either try for too much, or nothing at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find my way down Mount Tamalpais, which turns out to be its own challenge. The most direct route to Sausilito is a mountain bike trail. I’m a bit trepidatious about taking it with my bike weighed down, but take it anyway since I’m still thinking I could meet up with Tom. Also the sun is setting. I’m pleased to find everything, bike and body, still in one peice when I finally reach pavement. Then I just ride home, feeling bummed about the failed rendevious as I cross the bridge alone, but I’m simultaneously full of thanksgiving for having enjoyed such a great adventure.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[How come vs. what for]]></title><description><![CDATA[  Mmm, cozy. Anyone have any chestnuts? When people ask “Why…?” what they are really asking is at least two possible questions: “How come…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2017/11/22/how-come-vs-what-for</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2017/11/22/how-come-vs-what-for</guid><pubDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2017 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/fireplace-82d76273ab8bc5a8fd89eab1f8cf558c.gif&quot; alt=&quot;fireplace&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;Mmm, cozy. Anyone have any chestnuts?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people ask “Why…?” what they are really asking is at least two possible questions: “How come” and “what for”&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. For example, suppose you ask why is my TV showing logs burning in a fireplace? One answer is it creates the warm, cozy feeling of having a fireplace without needing to have an actual fireplace. That would be the “what for” answer. A weirder but still appropriate answer, given the question, would delve in to the technical details of how the information for representing the fireplace flows through the “series of tubes” to the computer connected to the TV, then flows from the computer to the TV, where atoms in liquid crystals are excited so they emit just the right frequency of light. You might think me a smart aleck if I answered the second way, but notice I’d still be answering your “why” question, though in a different sense of the word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it’s actually important to note the “how come/what for” distinction. Such as if we’re curious about why the simulation of a fireplace makes us feel cozy and warm. The “how come” sense might lead to an investigation of whats going on in the brain, whereas “what for” might lead to a consideration of the possible benefits of this tendency. Interestingly, Darwinian evolution simultaneously provides explanations for both versions of the question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;footnotes&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;small&gt;Dennett, Daniel C. (2013) &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://books.wwnorton.com/books/detail.aspx?ID=4294972441&quot;&gt;Intuition Pumps and other Tools for Thinking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Atlanta]]></title><description><![CDATA[The whole EventRay team, all three of us, got together in Atlanta this past week for a coding “sprint.” It was pretty successful on all…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2017/11/15/atlanta</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2017/11/15/atlanta</guid><pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2017 15:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;The whole EventRay team, all three of us, got together in Atlanta this past week for a coding “sprint.” It was pretty successful on all fronts: We accomplished five weeks of work, ate real bar-b-que&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;, chicken and waffles, and saw Marietta’s giant animatronic chicken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/bigchicken2-3aa4e2dd72ccd5fb2315d906a13d1a08.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;big chicken&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;It’s trying to eat me!&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/cafesanfrancisco-9e666aba82674be7e0bbd8f73901fe4e.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;doing work&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;Working from Cafe San Francisco (in Atlanta)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We stayed at a place near Chattahoochee River National Park, so I got to check another national park off my list. Went running on the trails there one morning and saw a giant buck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It dawned on me that Atlanta has a November Project tribe, and that I could make their Wednesday morning workout before my flight home so I booked a hotel near Ponce City Market, where the workout would be held. I set my alarm before going to bed, then I woke up and saw 6:22 on my clock, eight minutes before the start! I never sleep through my alarm. I leapt out of bed, got dressed, ran outside and started booking it. Now, it was a special workout in that everyone was encouraged to bring a few cans of food for a local charity. So there I was, running pell-mell in the early morning twilight, carrying my four cans of Green Giant. I get to the meeting spot expecting to see a big crowd. No one. A minute later I see a couple guys running, so I hazard to guess they’re also looking for the workout. Turns out they are, and they’re somewhat familiar with the area, so after a bit of wandering around we come to a park and see some people running with cans. Success!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workout was designed to incorporate the cans: running with one can in each hand, doing lunges while shoulder pressing the cans, you get it… During the workout I got my shirt “tagged”&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; with the Atlanta tribe’s decal: ATL inscribed in a peach, then afterwards got some coffee with the friendly leaders of the Atlanta tribe and another visitor from Austin, Texas. Then I booked it back to the hotel to get ready for my flight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/npatlgroup-2f99e53ad45f8ee7c4fc4a63f76744fa.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;NP ATL&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;The workout crew&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/npatlleaders-febb38783fb809a0f2de06041dde7fda.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;leaders, the traveller and me&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;Myself, two of the leaders and the visitor from Austin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;footnotes&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;small&gt;
First place we went to was a korean/southern bar-b-que fusion joint. We later decided that didn&apos;t really count and went to a place called D.B.A. in Virginia Highlands.
&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;small&gt;
Spray-painted. It&apos;s like a wearable passport book!
&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Is Facebook listening to us?]]></title><description><![CDATA[I don’t know, but you know they’re on to you when you start seeing ads for tin foil, or one proclaiming “we’re not eavesdropping, trust us…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2017/11/04/fb-spying</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2017/11/04/fb-spying</guid><pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I don’t know, but you know they’re on to you when you start seeing ads for tin foil, or one proclaiming “we’re not eavesdropping, trust us!” right after having a conversation about such speculations. According to my friend, &lt;a href=&quot;https://gimletmedia.com/episode/109-facebook-spying/&quot;&gt;the recent Reply All podcast&lt;/a&gt; does a good job covering this question and people’s stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have mixed feelings about Facebook in general. It certainly provides value, but we also trust them with a lot of potentially sensitive information. Another friend was telling me about how an old surname, which she had to fight to have legally removed from her records, randomly started popping up on her Facebook profile. Shades of 1984, specifically the power to revise history…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I had all the time or money, I would set everyone who wants one up with a blog like this. All the open source technology to replace Facebook (like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RSS&quot;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://indieweb.org/Webmention&quot;&gt;WebMention&lt;/a&gt;) with a network of websites owned by the individuals they represent already exists. It just takes time or money to set up, whereas you can create a Facebook account in a few minutes.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Deadline]]></title><description><![CDATA[If I seem flakey or unresponsive in the recent past or in the next couple months, it’s because we ( EventRay ) have an important deadline to…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2017/11/04/deadline</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2017/11/04/deadline</guid><pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2017 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;If I seem flakey or unresponsive in the recent past or in the next couple months, it’s because we (&lt;a href=&quot;http://eventray.com&quot;&gt;EventRay&lt;/a&gt;) have an important deadline to meet. There are two big events we &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to land as clients. There’s a lot of work we need to do on our product to meet the needs of those clients. Enough to keep us very busy every day, including weekends, until the first event launches in early January. So probably less exercise, socializing, days off for me until that work is done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sidebar: My Github contribution history
&lt;img src=&quot;/githubhistory-a3deb8b1fc516ec18a68f05ae61e8de9.gif&quot; alt=&quot;My Github contribution history graph&quot;&gt; Darker green means more work done. There’s about to be much darker green squares on the right side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever I have to do long bouts of programming work I tend to feel like a zombie when away from the computer. Perhaps that’s because those areas of the brain that I use when programming get all the exercise and the rest kinda goes to sleep, then when I’m doing other things like talking to human beings it takes a bit for them to wake up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s funny how deadlines work. They’re always stressful. A little stress inspires, but &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; much and I find myself getting anxious. Anxiety leads to more mistakes and myopic choices which make meeting the deadline harder. This is one of the latter sort of deadline, but I also know that being anxious is a choice, even if it’s hard to resist sometimes. So I’m fighting a battle on two fronts. One, completing the work itself. Two, resisting the thoughts about the work that create anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All that is to say, to those who know me, I may need your understanding and patience for a time (or more than usual.) In exchange I’ll be the best friend, family member and human being I know how to be.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Glacier National Park]]></title><description><![CDATA[Was in Glacier National Park in Montana earlier this month. We saw some mountain goats, some birds, and this guy:   Grizzly bear! 📷 by…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2017/10/29/glacier</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2017/10/29/glacier</guid><pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2017 17:18:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Was in Glacier National Park in Montana earlier this month. We saw some mountain goats, some birds, and this guy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/glacierbear-d404828f0b0f2f493370e0baaea971aa.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;the grizzly&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;Grizzly bear! 📷 by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/shingwongphotography/&quot;&gt;Shing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some other hikers coming the other direction warned us and we backtracked to the top of a hill then stopped to see if the bear was still following us. Turns out he was! I wasn’t sure how fast they can run and didn’t intend to find out, but of course the photographers had to snap some pics before fleeing more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We &lt;em&gt;bearly&lt;/em&gt; got to see any of the trail!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA["...my superior in some way..."]]></title><description><![CDATA[It has struck me that some great human beings have entered my orbit. I’ve been aware of this fact for some time, but for whatever reason it…]]></description><link>https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2017/10/29/first</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://patrickcanfield.com/blog/2017/10/29/first</guid><pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2017 17:13:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;It has struck me that some great human beings have entered my orbit. I’ve been aware of this fact for some time, but for whatever reason it’s been bubbling up in my mind more as of late, so it seems like a worthy subject to write about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know one guy who is always calm under pressure. “It will all work out for the best” he says with absolute conviction, and somehow it seems to always be true. He does not just idly hope, though. His mind is an Olympic gymnast, he can think quickly and flexibly to turn a bad situation around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another friend is very analytical. He asks perceptive wayfinding questions that bring clarity to messy problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone else uses his powers for good&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. I was in a cafe the other day where piano music was playing. I thought it was a recording, then I turn around and see that there’s a grand piano in the corner, and he’s the one playing! I had no idea he could do that. I’m often surprised by this person’s random abilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s this one friend who has great perspective. Sometimes things don’t go according to plan. I get frustrated, he just laughs. It’s good to be reminded that most things are not worth worrying about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there’s a more recent acquaintance who’s smile and gentle demeanor makes me feel welcome and safe. She asks thoughtful questions that get me thinking in compelling new trajectories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are just some of the luminaries I’ve been fortunate to know lately. I can at least be a good appreciator of their qualities and hope that they rub off on me. Hopefully there are people in your life who you regard as superior in some way. If not, go find them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;footnotes&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Not to say the others use theirs for evil, that is.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;The title is taken from Ralph Waldo Emerson: “In my walks, every man I meet is my superior in some way, and in that I learn from him.”&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>